[
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Call, look, continue, get old, how long, keep jumping, kill, nod, keep sitting, solution, begin making pet, animal, catch</font> <br>একদিন এক বাঘ আরেকটা বাঘকে ডেকে বললো, \"দ্যাখো ভাই, আর চলছে না । বয়েস হচ্ছে, এভাবে আর কতদিন লাফিয়ে যাবো বলো তো ? জন্তু আর মারতে পারি না ভালো করে\"। অন্য বাঘটা মাথা নেড়ে বললো, \"তুমি ঠিকই বলেছো । কিন্তু যদি আমরা বসে থাকি তবে তো আর খাবার পাবো না । উপায় কী আছে\"? তখন প্রথম বাঘ বললো, \"দ্যাখো, আমরা যদি মানুষের মতো অন্য জানোয়ার পুষতে শুরু করি ? সেটা কেমন হয়\" ? দ্বিতীয় বাঘ বললো, \"কিন্তু আমরা জন্তু পুষবো কী করে ? আগে তো জানোয়ারদের ধরতে হবে । আমরা কি তা করতে পারব\" ?",
    "answer":"One day a tiger called another one to say, “Look brother, this can not continue anymore. I am getting old, tell me how long do I keep jumping ? I can not kill animals too well anymore.”. The other tiger nodded its head and said, “You are right. But if we keep sitting, we won’t get food. So what is the solution ?”. Then the first tiger said, “Look, what if we begin making other animals pet just as a man does? How is it ?”. The second tiger said, “But how will we make animals pet ? We have to catch the animals first. Can we do that ?”"
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Think, catch, laugh, get mad, learn, steal, speak, in this matter</font> <br>এবারে প্রথম বাঘ একটু চিন্তা করলো । তারপর বললো, ”দ্যাখো ভাই, জানোয়াররা তো আর মানুষের কাছে এসে বলে না, আমাদের ধরো । মানুষই ওদের ধরে । তাহলে আমরাও ধরবো । “ দ্বিতীয় বাঘ হেসে বললো, ”এখন-ই আমাদের মাথা খারাপ হয়ে যাচ্ছে, আর তুমি ভাবছো তুমি জানোয়ার পুষবে !” এবারে প্রথম বাঘ বললো, ”হয় আমাদের ধরতে শিখতে হবে, নাহলে মানুষের কাছ থেকে চুরি করতে হবে । আমরা এ ব্যাপারে সিংহের সঙ্গে কথা বলতে পারি । যদি উনি হাতির সঙ্গে কথা বলেন তো ভাল হয় । তখন আর আমরা যাব না, হাতিই চুরি করবে মানুষের পোষা জানোয়ার ।“",
    "answer":"Then the first tiger thought a little. And he said, “Look brother, animals do not come to humans and say, catch me. Humans only catch them. So we will also catch them.” The second tiger said laughing, “Now only we are getting mad, and you are thinking of making pets!” Then the first tiger said, “Either we have to learn to catch or we have to steal from humans. We can speak to lion in this matter. If it can speak to elephant, it will be good. Then we will not have to go, elephant only will steal pets of humans.”"
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Quarrel, listen, breathe heavy, swimming, learn, get into, jump, get drowned, passing by, catch, right, hear, show</font> <br>দুই বন্ধুতে খুব ঝগড়া করছে । একে অপরের কথা শুনবে না । দুজনেই হাঁফাচ্ছে । ঝগড়াটা হলো সাঁতার কাটা নিয়ে । একজন বলে, \"যদি সাঁতার না শিখি, জলে নামবো কি করে\" ? অন্যজন বলে, \"জলে না ঝাঁপালে সাঁতার শিখবি কি করে\" ? একজন বলে, \"জলে নামলেই তো ডুবে যাবো, তখন মৃত্যু\"। আরেকজন বলে, \"ওই জন্যেই তো সাঁতার শিখবি\"। সামনে দিয়ে যাচ্ছিলেন একজন বৃদ্ধ লোক । দুজনে তাকে ধরলো, \"বলুন, আমরা কে ঠিক\" ? উনি সব শুনে বললেন, \"বাবা, জলে না নেমে কেমন করে সাঁতার কাটবে, একবার দেখাও দেখি\" !",
    "answer":"Two friends are quarreling a lot. No one will listen to the other. Both are breathing heavily. The quarrel is about swimming. One says, “If I do not learn swimming, how do I get into water?”. The other says, “If you do not jump into water, how do you learn swimming?”.  One says, “Once I get into water, I shall get drowned, it will be death for me then.”. The other says, “You will have to learn swimming because of that only.” A man was passing by before them. Both of them caught him, “Tell us, who is right between us?” He heard everything and said, “Son, show me how you will swim without getting into water.”"
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Result, out, fail, pass, take tuition, sell, buy, vegetables, take bath, take food, change, danger, become, listen</font> <br>পরীক্ষার ফল বেরিয়েছে । অজিত ফেল করেছে ক্লাসে । অজিতের বন্ধু পলাশ পাস করেছে । অজিত তিনজন স্যারের কাছে পড়ে । পলাশের কোনো শিক্ষক নেই, স্কুলের শিক্ষক ছাড়া । তাছাড়া পলাশ সকালে বাজারে আনাজপাতি নিয়ে বেচতে বসে । বেচাকেনা শেষ হলে স্কুলে আসে । কোনো কোনোদিন ওর স্নান পর্যন্ত হয় না, খাওয়াও হয় না । পলাশ অনেকবার অজিতকে বলেছে, \"নিজেকে না পাল্টালে তুই কিন্তু বিপদে পড়বি । তোর মতো যদি আমার স্যার থাকতো, আমি প্রথম বা দ্বিতীয় বা অন্ততঃ তৃতীয় হতাম !\"  কিন্তু অজিত কোনোদিনই পলাশের কথা শোনেনি ।",
    "answer":"Examination result is out. Ajit has failed in the class. Ajit’s friend Palash has passed. Ajit takes tuition from three teachers. Palash has no private tutor, except school teachers. Besides that, Palash sits at the market to sell vegetables. After selling and buying he comes to school. Some days he can not take bath even, can not take food either. Palash has said to Ajit many times, “If you do not change yourself, you will be in danger. If I had private tutors like you, I would become first, second or at least third.”. But Ajit never listened to Palash."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Plan, organise, make, pandal, bringing idol, cooking, feed people, agree, divide, work, help, beautify, decorate, prepare, bring, trouble, begin, want, understand</font> <br>ছেলেরা একটা পরিকল্পনা করলো,  এবারে সরস্বতীপুজোয় তারা নিজেরাই সব করবে - প্যান্ডেল করা, ঠাকুর আনা,  রান্না,  খাওয়ানো ইত্যাদি সব । মেনে নিল না মেয়েরা । তারা বললো, \"কেন ছেলেরা সব করবে, মেয়েরা কি পারেনা ?\"  শেষে স্কুল ভাগ করে দিল কাজ । ছেলেরা করবে প্যান্ডেল, ঠাকুর আনা, রান্নায় জোগাড় দেওয়া । মেয়েরা সাজানো,  আল্পনা দেওয়া, রান্না করা ইত্যাদি । প্যান্ডেল তৈরী ভালোই হলো । ঠাকুরও এলো । ঝামেলা হলো রান্নার সময় ।  মেয়েরা যা চায় ছেলেরা বোঝেনা - কারণ তারা কোনোদিন এসব করেনি ।",
    "answer":"The boys made a plan that they would organize Saraswati Puja on their own this time – making pandal, bringing idol, cooking, feeding people etc and all. The girls did not agree. They said, “Why would the boys do everything, can’t the girls do anything?” Finally the school divided the work. The boys would make pandal, bring idol and help in cooking. And the girls would beautify, decorate and cook. The pandal was prepared well. Idol was brought too. But the trouble began at the time of cooking. The boys do not understand what the girls want – because they never did them before."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Open, enter, start, walk, cut, hear, chirping, fight, drink, paint, laugh, dance, finish, put, make</font> <br>সকাল ১০টায় চিড়িয়াখানা খুলতে আমরা ঢুকে হাঁটতে শুরু করলাম । দুপাশের গাছগুলো ছোটো করে কাটা । লেকের সামনে যেতে প্রচুর পাখির আওয়াজ শুনতে পেলাম । কয়েকটা পাখি নিজেদের মধ্যে লড়াই করছিল । ওখানে একটু বসে আমরা কফি খেলাম । দিশা খাতা খুলে আঁকতে শুরু করলো । দূরে একদল বাচ্চা খুব হাসছিল ভাল্লুক দেখে । কেউ বলছিল, \"মা ভাল্লুক কী খায়\" ? কেউ বলছিল, \"বাবা, ভাল্লুকটা কখন নাচবে\" ? আঁকা শেষ করে দিশা খাতাটা তার ব্যাগে রাখলো ।  দিশা বেশ সুন্দর করেছিল আঁকাটা ।",
    "answer":"As the zoo had opened at ten in the morning, we had entered and started walking. The trees on both sides had been cut small. When we had gone before the lake, we had heard chirping of many birds. Some birds had been fighting among themselves.  We had sat there to drink some coffee. Disha had opened a copy and had started painting. At a distance looking at bears a group of kids was laughing. Some was saying, “Mother, what do bears eat?”. Some other was saying, “Father, when will the bear dance?”. Disha then finished the painting and put it into her bag. She has made the painting quite beautiful."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Move, rented house, tell, do, keep, furniture, take, pull, carry, push, fall, got broken, cry, fear, tell, damage, done, see, play</font> <br>আমরা ভাড়া বাড়ি থেকে নিজেদের বাড়িতে উঠে যাচ্ছি । মা আমাদের সবাইকে বলে দিয়েছে যে আমাদের প্রত্যেককে কাজ করতে হবে । বড় বাক্সগুলোয় এখন কিছু আসবাবপত্র রাখা হচ্ছে । তারপর সেগুলো ট্রলিতে করে দাদা টেনে বাইরে নিয়ে যাবে । হরিকাকা কাঁচের থালার বাক্সটা নিয়ে যাচ্ছিলো,  হঠাৎ ভাই এসে পেছন থেকে ধাক্কা দিলো ।  বাক্সটা হাত থেকে পড়ে গিয়ে চার পাঁচটা থালা ভেঙে গেলো । ভাই ভয়ে কেঁদে ফেললো । মা এসে ভাইকে খুব কিছু বলল না - কেবল বললো, ”বাবা, খেলার জন্যে কোনো ক্ষতি না হয়, সেটা দেখো” ।",
    "answer":"We are moving from rented house to our own house. Mother has told all of us that everyone will have to do work. Some furniture are being kept in the big boxes. Then my elder brother will take them outside pulling them by a trolley. Hari Uncle was carrying the box having glass plates; suddenly my brother pushed him from behind. The box fell from the hands and four-five plates got broken. Brother cried in fear. Mother came but did not tell much to brother – only said, “Son, see that no damage is done for your play.”"
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Monk, talk, smile, search, find, leave, touch, forehead, like, turn away, get to know, fold knees, count, plan, save, drop, die, hate, ask, close, happen</font> <br>পাড়ায় এক সাধু এসেছেন । কথা কম বলেন, কেবল হাসেন । কারোর প্রশ্নের উত্তরে বলেন, “যা খুঁজছিস তা একদিন পাবি”। কাউকে কপালে হাত ঠেকিয়ে ছেড়ে দেন । আবার কারোর প্রশ্ন পছন্দ না হলে মুখ ঘুরিয়ে নেন । একজন বৃদ্ধ লোক সাধুর খবর পেয়ে এসেছেন ; তাঁর সামনে হাঁটু মুড়ে বসে পড়লেন । সাধু কীসব গুনে বললেন, \"তোকে বাঁচাতে পারি যদি তুই তোর বাজে পরিকল্পনাটা বাতিল করিস । নাহলে তুই মারা যাবি\"। শুনে লোকটি কাঁদতে শুরু করল । বললো, \"বাবা, ভাই আমাকে এতো ঘৃণা করে যে ওকে আমি বাড়ি ছেড়ে চলে যেতে বলেছি\"। সাধু চোখ বুজলেন ।  এবারে লোকটি বললেন, \"বাবা, তুমি যা বলবে তাই হবে\"।",
    "answer":"A monk has come to our locality. He talks less, only smiles. To someone’s question he answers, “Someday you will get what you are searching for.”. He leaves someone touching hand on his forehead. Sometimes he turns his face away if he does not like one’s question.  An old man has come getting to know about the monk; he sat down before the monk folding his knees. The monk counted something and said, “I can save you if you drop your bad plan. Otherwise you will die”. Hearing this, the man started crying. He said, “Father, my brother hates me so much that I have asked him to leave the house.”. The monk closed his eyes. Then the man said, “Father, What you say will happen.”"
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Rise, paint, travel, fill, beforehand, share, wait, drive, choose, miss, send, chew, listen, feel, smell, sing, tune, add, win, arrive, journey, end</font> <br>পূব দিকে সূর্য উঠেছে । আকাশটা যেন কেউ কমলা রঙে এঁকে দিয়েছে । আমরা বেড়াতে যাচ্ছি ঘাটশিলা । মা একটা ঝুড়ি ফল আর অন্য খাবারে ভর্তি করেছে । আগেই বলে দিয়েছিল যে আমরা যেন খাবার ভাগ করে খাই । বাড়ির বাইরে সবাই গাড়ির জন্যে অপেক্ষা করছি । বাবা গাড়ি চালিয়ে ঘাটশিলা নিয়ে যাবে । জানলার পাশের জায়গাটা আমি বেছে নিয়েছি ।  ঠাকুমা আসতে পারেনি আমাদের সঙ্গে । আমরা সবাই খুব মিস করছি আমাদের ঠাকুমাকে । রাঁধুনীকে মা আগেই ঘাটশিলা পাঠিয়ে দিয়েছে । জানলার ধারে বসে বাবলগাম চিবোচ্ছি আর গান শুনছি । শীত আসছে,  আমার বেশ ঠান্ডা লাগছে । চারপাশে ফুলের গন্ধ । আমরা ‘অন্তাক্ষরী’ খেলা শুরু করলাম । অনুদি ভুল সুরে গান করছিল, তাতে নতুন নতুন মজা যোগ হচ্ছিল । কিন্তু অনুদিই জিতলো শেষে । ঘাটশিলার বাগানবাড়িতে পৌঁছে আমাদের যাত্রা শেষ হলো ।",
    "answer":"The sun has risen in the east. As if someone has painted the sky in orange. We are traveling to Ghatsila. Mother has filled up a basket with fruits and other food. She told us beforehand to share and eat the food.  All of us are waiting for car outside the house. Father will drive to take us to Ghatshila.  I have chosen a seat beside window. Grandmother is not able to come with us. All of us are missing our Grandmother. Mother has already sent the cook to Ghatshila. Sitting beside window I am chewing bubblegum and listening to music. Winter is coming, and I am feeling cold. There is smell of flowers around. We started playing ‘Antakkhari’. Anudi was singing in wrong tune, and it was adding new fun. But Anudi only won finally. Arriving at the farmhouse of Ghashila our journey ended."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Start, clean, corner, use, order, help, idle, move, set, look</font> <br>আজ সকাল থেকে আমরা বাড়ি পরিষ্কার শুরু করেছি । বাড়ির প্রতিটা কোনা আর জিনিস পরিষ্কার করতে হবে আমাদের । এমনকি আমরা রোজ যা ব্যবহার করি যেমন জুতো, জামা, প্যান্ট – সেগুলোও পরিষ্কার আছে কিনা দেখতে হবে। মায়ের আদেশ, \"সবাই সবাইকে সাহায্য করবে, কেউ বসে থাকবে না\"। প্রতিটা আসবাব আমরা সরিয়ে রাখছি । পরিষ্কার করে আবার সেগুলো ঠিক জায়গায় রাখছে মানদামাসি আর হরিকাকা । কী সুন্দর লাগছে গোটা বাড়ি পরিষ্কার হবার পর !",
    "answer":"Since today morning we have started cleaning our house. We have to clean every corner and every item of the house. We have to check that even what we use everyday – shoes, shirts, pants etc – are clean or not. Mother’s order is – everybody will help everybody, nobody will sit idle. We are moving each furniture. Cleaning them Manada Aunt and Hari Uncle are setting them right again. How beautiful the house looks after cleaning !"
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Raining, watch, fly, cook, different, get, smell, slip, return, have lunch, tell, allow</font> <br>কাল বিকেল থেকে বৃষ্টি পড়ছে । আজ স্কুলে যেতে পারিনি । জানলার পাশে বসে বৃষ্টি দেখছি । কতগুলো পাখি সামনে দিয়ে উড়ে গেলো । মা আজ অন্যরকম কিছু রান্না করছে, গন্ধ পাওয়া গেল । বাবা বাড়ি চলে এলো । রাস্তায় পা পিছলে পড়ে  গেছে বলে অফিস যেতে পারেনি । খুব মজা - দুপুরে সবাই একসঙ্গে খাবো । তারপর বাবা গল্প বলবে বলেছে । তারপর টিভিতে কার্টুন দেখতে দেবে বলেছে মা ।",
    "answer":"It has been raining since yesterday afternoon. I could not go to school today. I am watching rain sitting by the window. Some birds have flown before me. Mother is cooking something different today; I am getting the smell. Father returns home. He could not go to office because he slipped on the road. What a fun – we will have lunch together. Father has said that he will tell a story after that. Then mother will allow me to watch cartoon on TV."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Competition, start, session, end, make to semifinal, get into final, brilliantly, lose, play, distribute, draw, paint</font> <br>আজ স্বাধীনতা দিবস । ছুটির দিন । তাই পাড়ায় ফুটবল প্রতিযোগিতা । সকাল সাড়ে ন’টায় শুরু হলো খেলা । ১০টা টিম খেলছে । দুপুর দেড়টায় প্রথম পর্ব শেষ হলো । ৪টে দল সেমিফাইনালে উঠলো । শেষে ফাইনালে উঠলো আমাদের দল আর রায়পাড়া । কিন্তু আমাদের দল দারুণ খেলায় ফাইনালে রায়পাড়া হেরে গেলো দুগোলে । অনুষ্ঠান শেষে পুরষ্কার  বিতরণ হলো । আগামীকাল বসে আঁকো প্রতিযোগিতা ।  সেখানে আমার ভাই ছবি আঁকবে ।",
    "answer":"It is Independence Day today. It is a holiday. So we have a football competition in our locality. Match started at 9-30 AM. Ten teams are playing. The first session ended at 1-30 in the afternoon. Four teams had made it to the semifinal. Then finally our team and Raypara got into the final. But as our team played brilliantly, Raypara lost by two goals. At the end of the function prizes were distributed. Tomorrow there will be a sit-and-draw competition. My brother will paint a picture there."
  }
]